[Dan] right, hello and welcome everyone to this episode
of the MagNetZ seminar series! Before we start
let's have a quick look at the format of today's
seminar. As always, it will be a 25 to 30 minutes
presentation that's going to be followed by 10 to
15 minutes of time that will be open for questions.
After this we will have a short informal time for
for catch-up and chat that will not be recorded.
For this week's seminar we are excited to have
Boris Robert from GFZ Potsdam in lovely Germany
who will talk about "High velocity polar
wonder in West Africa and its implications
on the Ediacaran magnetic field". Boris if you
could share your screen then the floor is
all yours. [Boris] okay perfect. So thank you very much
for your invitation. I'm running a bit out of
battery so I'm gonna just switch off my camera.
Hello, everyone. So today I'm gonna talk about
data paleomagnetic data and geochronological
data from West Africa and discuss the hypothesis
of True Polar Wander and perturbation
of magnetic field during the Ediacaran.
This work is a collaborative work and the
co-workers are listed in the bottom of the
of the slide. So let's first start about.. let's
first define the Ediacaram. Ediacaran is the last
geological period of the Precambrian and it
lasted from 635 to 538 million years. Many major
phenomena occurred in the superficial
layers of the planet during that period,
including rapid evolutionary biological changes,
like the appearance of the Ediacaran fauna,
major disruption in the carbon cycle, with the
largest delta 13c excursion recorded in carbonates,
and also many glaciations observed
in continents, that could
indicate a global scale glaciations, and
a major forcing for these superficial
processes could be paleogeography. And during that
period of time, the Ediacaran, there is the last
final fragmentation of the supercontinent
Rodinia and also the amalgamation of Gondwana,
which is going to be a major landmass constituting
of Pangea. But the palogeography for that period
of time is very.. is still very debated and
this is the topic of this this presentation.
The reason for this complex.. for this debate is
partly because of the paleomagnetic record that
is very complex to interpret because it is
very highly scattered. And to illustrate this idea
here I show the paleomagnetic data from Laurentia,
the North American craton of that time. So here
it's a compilation of 2011, so there are a bit
paleopole since then that have been published,
but the main idea remains the same that the
paleomagnetic poles are very scattered and seem to
be organized into two groups of poles, shown here
in pink and green, divided by about 90 degrees
and of a similar age. If these poles are used
to reconstruct the position of the continent,
Laurentia would have moved from a high
latitude to low latitude very fast, with
some period reaching a velocity of more than
meter per year, which seems very..way more fast..way
faster than what we observe for the more recent
times and it seems difficult to be explained by
what we know about the physics of plate motion.
Some people have proposed that there could be
True Polar Wander as an explanation for this
large Polar Wander Path and to Polar Wander.
This is the movement of the Earth relative to the
spin axis and this.. the sketch is showing this..so
before True Polar Wander we have here on the left,
and after a large Polar Wander of 90 degrees.
We can see the entire surface with which
has moved relative to the spin axis.
This process is produced by results from
the conservation of the angular momentum.
And on geological time scales it is produced
by the changes in the distribution of mass
heterogeneities inside the mantle, produced
by mantle convection. And this is the light
material in plumes and the dense material in slabs
basically. Another hypothesis to explain this
data set is the presence of artifacts in the
data and notably the existence of unrecognized
remagnetizations. For example, one possibility
could be that one of the two groups of poles
would be affected by a remagnetizazion. For
example, if it was the case for the pink group,
we would get back to much lower plate motion
where Laurentia would stay at low latitude in this
example. Another hypothesis is the hypothesis
of perturbation of the magnetic field.
Where..so this idea relies on
the fact that, for the Ediacaran, the magnetic
field could be very different than the one we have
today, and could be dominated by a magnetic dipole
oscillating from an axial position, as we have
today, to a position where the magnetic dipole
is lying in the equatorial plane, as we see on
the sketch in the right part of the the slide.
These two states.. you could have oscillation
between these two states pretty fast. So
in this presentation I'm going to try to test
these different hypotheses so the hypothesis of
remagnetization magnetic field perturbations and
True Polar Wander, and something important is that
if it was magnetic field perturbations or True
Polar Wander at the origin of this paleomagnetic data
set, we should see this large Polar Wander Path
a lot on every continent at the same time, while if
it was a re-magnetization that should be a local
process or regional process. So that's why
I conducted a paleomagnetic study in Morocco,
to sample paleomagnetic sample on pyroclastic rocks
in the anti-Atlas, which are representative of
the West African craton. Morocco is located in the
northern tip of the West African craton, here, shown
in orange in this little sketch, this little figure.
In the anti-Atlas there
are layers where outcrop Precambrian rocks and
notably Ediacaran rocks. And we sample these
pyroclastic rocks. They dated between 575 and 530
million years. On the right there is a picture
showing these successions of pyroclastic deposits.
We obtained several paleomagnetic
directions from this study. The first
component, A, that has been acquired during the
folding event, and the folding event in this region
is of Ercininian age, so related to the collision
between Gondwana and Laurentia,
about 300 million years ago. We also identify two
other paleomagnetic directions B1 and C that are
that have been identified in the middle and upper
part of the group Ouarzazate for B1, and in the lower part
of the Ouarzazate group in regarding the component
C. Both directions are supported by a positive
fold test and B1 is supported also by a positive
intra-formational conglomerate tests, and so
based on this information, we
interpreted these directions as being primary.
Here are the paleomagnetic poles calculated
from these directions, so B1, C and A.
And something important was to compare
this paleomagnetic poles with the other
paleomagnetic data that has been published for the
West African craton. And for this, we use selection
criteria to select the best paleomagnetic
data. So an age error, for example,
for the pole less than 20 million years
and a95 less than 16 degrees etc. So here
are..the here is the result we obtained where we
identified that a lot of paleomagnetic poles were
re-magnetized during the Ercinian collision.
Finally, we selected one pole from the literature
dated at 650 million years and that display with
the other paleomagnetic poles we obtained
this study a large loop between 615 and 565
million years with an apex at 571 million years.
We also replaced the above Polar Wander Path
for Laurentia based on a similar..
the same selection criteria and we found a
like a large oscillation as well in Laurentia
between 615 and 565 million years, and also large
oscillations in Baltica, so the North European
craton, with oscillations between 615
600 565 and 550 million years. This large..
we wanted to compare this then this
large oscillation between the different
blocks by superimposing them, and this is
what we what is represented on this figure.
So in blue are the poles from West Africa,
in orange are the poles from Baltica, and cyan
are the poles from Laurentia. We can see that there
is a good match between the different
Polar Wander Path, where the poles at
615 are together, poles around 595 575 million years
are together, and poles at 565 are together. So
there is good correlation between Apparent Polar Wander Paths
in time and amplitude. If we look at the
paleogeography obtained with this fit, we also obtain
a paleogeography which is consistent
which is consistent with geology, and that is
where there is the Iapetus Ocean that separates
these different blocks that has just opened.
So this consistency with paleogeography
also supports the dipolar nature of the
magnetic fields, and also seem to indicate that
there is no re-magnetization in this data set.
We then try to test the True Polar Wonder
hypothesis by combining paleogeography and
simple mantle dynamic simulations, and by
trying to find scenarios of mantle convection
that could explain.. that could produce True
Polar Wander that explained the paleomagnetic
data. So we investigated a lot of different
scenarios and we found that a possible way
to explain the data is by changing dramatically
the distribution of subduction zones at the
beginning of the Ediacaran. So you can see these
two paleogeographic reconstructions here with
the activation of a large gather of subduction
in red here surrounding the continents at 635
million years, and this would produce a
large destabilization of the inertia and
would produce a large True Polar Wander, as shown
here in black, that at first order can explain
the paleomagnetic data shown here in blue. But
still in this very extreme change in mantle
convection we could not obtain velocities
higher than three to four degrees per million
years, and that means and this is because of
the viscosity of the mantle
that breakthe deformation of the planet
and then the resulting True Polar Wander.
So an important parameter then to further
test this hypothesis of True Polar Wander
is the velocity of paleomagnetic changes. So as I said,
True Polar Wander could not be faster than some
degrees per million years, while we could expect
in the case of magnetic field perturbations that
the velocity of changes to be way faster and this
is for example illustrated by magnetic reversals,
where we can have magnetic changes of the order
of 10 degrees per thousand years. And so
to further investigate this hypothesis,
we obtain new geochronological data to better date
these large paleomagnetic changes because the
available geochronological data could not
distinguish between these two hypotheses.
So we obtained seven new ages in
the Ouazazate group, in collaboration with
Fernando Corfu who made the lab experiments at
the University of Oslo. So we re-dated samples
in the lower part of the Ouazazate group,
for basically the pole giving a lower [than] expected,
latitude, and the data also in the upper part
and for the other pole, and also data in between to
have an age progression and test the evolution of
the geochronological data with stratigraphy. So here are
some of the concordia results so in some cases we
found very good agreement between most of the
dates within the sample, and this is the case of
the sample in the upper upper left corner
with yielding to a an age of 569 million years.
In some other cases it was more dispersed, as
it is shown here on the upper right corner, where
the dates are more spread and could be interpreted
as two groups..two age plateaus at 569 and 565
million years. So here is the summary of
all the the dates we obtained for each
sample, from stratigraphically older the right to
younger left, and each column is one sample.
We can see that there is a high dispersion in
samples that could be explained by two process,
first the existence of xenocrysts but
also ante-xenocrysts which are crystals that
crystallized in the magmatic chamber a bit before
the extrusion of the volcanic rocks, and that
would have a slightly older age then. The
presence of xenocryst and antecrysts is a typical
of explosive volcanism, as we are studying
here. But there is also the presence
potentially of lead loss, putting dates to a
younger age than age of emplacement. This lead
loss could be produced by the Ercinian orogeny
that has been responsible for a low temperature
heating of the rocks, and we could not.. because
of the proximity of the age of emplacement of
the rocks and the Ercinian orogeny
in time the discordia would be parallel to the
concordia curves. And so it they are difficult
to be distinguished but what we can rely
on is the age plateaus in samples that should
be representative of the age of emplacement.
Because of this dispersion still
we constructed two end-member age progressions,
a red age progressions that produce a
very fast..quick emplacement of this..between
these two quick time gap..between the emplacement
of the two formations and which relies on the best
best data, and another age progression, here shown
in orange, that would be the age progression
that yield to the largest time gap between the
emplacement of the two formations. And like that
we can bracket the maximum ages of emplacement
of these two formations. So because of these two
age progressions we have two sets of ages
for the two poles, the red paths yield
an age of 571 and 569 million years, and orange
/yellow yield an age of 575 and 566
million years. So the question now is what is
the velocity between the velocity associated.
So to do this we did a Monte Carlo..
we followed the Monte Carlo approach
to take into account the uncertainties as
a special uncertainties of the paleomagnetic
pole, so the a95, but also the uncertainties
related to the geochronological data we just
obtained. So we drew ten thousand paleo
magnetic..synthetic palaomagnetic poles from
each of the two distribution, and we also sample
randomly an age based on the distribution associated
with the geochronological data. And this is the
results we obtain for in the orange age progression
and for the red age progression, and
this is different velocities that has been..
that have been calculated. So we can see that the
median velocity for the orange progression is of
11.6 degrees per million year, and it 56.8 degree
per million years for the red age progression.
So if we compare now this True Polar Wander..
no this sorry..this velocity estimates
with what we know about True Polar Wander, so
the observations of True Polar Wander but also
the velocities that we can obtain in numerical
simulations, this is what we..that's compared on
this little panel, where the scale is reduced from
0 to 12 degree per million years. So we can see
that the velocities we obtain are way higher than
the True Polar Wander estimated for the last 550
million years, at about 1 degree per million year.
We can also see that the velocity estimates we
obtain are also very.. much higher than the
best True Polar Wander fitting model that
we obtained in our study of 2018, where
with the large reactivation of the seduction zone.
And the largest estimate I found in the
literature for True Polar Wander velocity is
the study of Creveling et al. in 2012, and
they obtained velocities of about
eight degrees per million year,that
could be quite close to the median value, but this
type of true polar wonder is of low amplitude
of about 40 degrees, and could not explain the
90 degrees um amplitude found in the
data but in any case our preferred age progression
in red is way above any of these estimates. So
it seems then that it is difficult to reconcile
this velocity estimates with the True
Polar Wander hypothesis. And if it is not
True Polar Wander, could it be magnetic
field perturbations? and interestingly
is that the distribution of paleomagnetic poles
that we obtain from our selection could be
explained by the hypothesis of equatorial
and axial dipole because we have.. we see
these two groups of poles, and so that could
that could work. Interestingly since a decade,
a lot of new studies have shown that the magnetic
field during the Ediacaran could be very atypical
notably based on paleointensity estimate.
So this graphic is shown the paleointensity
estimates for the Ediacaran and cambrian, and we
see that values less than 10 of the present-day
magnetic field value are reported, and there are
also a very high reversal rate that has been
also observed for this period of time. And it has
even been proposed that this perturbations of this
data could show that there was the
crystallization of the inner core
associated with these perturbations, at the origin
of these perturbations of the magnetic field.
So okay, if this hypothesis of actual equatorial
dipole is the right one, where would
be the the the axial dipole component?
And the way to answer this question is to
compare this the paleogeography we obtained by
fitting these two groups of poles with paleo
geographies obtained for later times, when we think
that the magnetic field was behaving normally.
And so we can compare the paleogeography for
the Ediacaran with the paleogeography obtained at 500
million years, for example. And at 500 million
years Laurentia is at low latitude, Baltica is at
mid latitude and West Africa is at high altitude.
And this is consistent with the latitudes obtained
in the case where we consider this group of poles
being the axial dipole component where West Africa
is at high latitude, Baltica at mid-latitude
and Laurentia at low latitude. So based on this
comparison, we could interpret these two groups
of poles as being the axial dipole here and the
equatorial dipole. Of course this comparison uh
is only valid if we consider that the paleogeography
hasn't evolved too much between 565 570 to 500
million years. Another interesting observation is that
it has been observed that there are glacial
deposits in the anti-Atlas, so in Morocco
between 590 and 580 million years,
and if this group of pole was
indeed produced by an axial dipole that
would place west africa at high latitude, and
that would be consistent with the existence
of this glacial deposits at that time.
So to conclude this presentation, I showed that
paleomagnetic data display large Polar Wander
path during Ediacaran in West Africa, and
that this large Polar Wander seems to be
global because also observing other
blocks like Laurentia and Baltica..
We obtained a new geochronological data that
support a very fast Polar Wander which seems to be
difficult to be explained by True
Polar Wandor and instead it could be
explained by perturbations of magnetic field
and for example a magnetic field dominated
by a magnetic dipole oscillating from an axial
to an equatorial position. Thank you very much
[Dan]thank you very much for this great talk! let's all
give you much a round of applause for Boris here.
Now we will have 10 to 15 minutes for some
questions, so if we have any questions please
let me show you a hand.
While we're waiting I can I can start
off with one. I've been following your
your stuff in West Africa a bit and it's really
interesting. So now that you have the models
that that don't agree with True Polar Wander
have you have you come across any rocks that
that you think would be suitable
to do intensity studies as well on them?
[Boris] So, this is mostly hematite that is carrying the
magnetization in most of the rocks so and we
it was pretty rare to see a single domain
magnetite that could be suitable. I think..
I think for this reason the data..
the rocks would not be perfect for paleo
intensity, but i should get look back to this data
again, because there there could be some uh
but i should look at this again more closely.
[Dan] what's interesting i mean non non-ideal
rock for intensities are very common yeah
so but that would be great that
[Boris] would be great to obtain yeah
intensity data on this on
these rocks definitely yeah
maybe for the the cambrian the cambrian
they could be yeah I can i can
[Dan] all right, we have Mary who is muted [Mary] yeah sorry
this is only just I've just missed something
stupid here, but if you go back to slides 20
and 18 19, when you've got the yellow and red age
progressions [Boris] yeah here [Mary] yeah well I guess it's
actually on slide 19 which is where you've got the
the two geochrons with the two digits oh yeah yeah
19. yeah i was just wondering like i didn't fully
follow how you got these two different what the
differences between these two age progressions,
[Boris] yeah so this is um basically I because I
interpreted the data based on age plateaus and so
in some samples plateaus are there is one plateau..
one unique plateau.. in this case for example
and in this case but in some other samples it's
more complex, and it seems that there could be
two plateaus for sample 263, and sowhat
what I try to do because of this dispersion
is to try different scenarios one two extreme
cases, one which would which would have the
the quickest time of the smallest time
gap between the emplacement of these
two formations, the red age progression ,
and one which would lead the largest
time gap between these two formations, basically to
try to uh to reflect at best the data sets.
[Mary] cool so that means that the
the yellow one, which is the um
sorry the yellow one is the yes,
the minimum time between them
[Boris] yeah yeah and also something something that
could be a bit confusing here is that uh
the paleomagnetic poles are obtained in these
two. These two samples are representative of
one paleomagnetic pole. So this is not exactly
the change of formation that matters here
but these two samples and these [other] two samples
because in between we didn't observe
the paleomagnetic directions that we are
interested in, and so there is here a gap
stratigraphically. So also something we try to
do is to use the stratigraphy information to
make our choices about the age progression ,to
try to to be the most consistent as possible.
[Dan] all right. thank you Mary
thanks for that. Andrei yeah
[Andrei] Boris, thank you for the great talk, very
interesting. Well, I have actually two
related questions. Were you able to estimate.. the
have you observed the reversals? [Boris] yes we we observed
[Andrei] and could you estimate the reversal rate if
you for your different age constraints?
[Boris] no no we could not, because so basically this
is this kind of successions we worked on
and we don't really know
the age between this is different
[Andrei] yeah but for for the separate
fragments up and down separately no
or or you just or you just see the one
polarity in the upper part and another in the
lower part, do you? [Boris] It was more in some
flows were reversed and some flows were normal.
And also these these rocks are deposited in
aerial environment, so we don't have sediments
in between, we don't see. And so it's it's very
hard to know the age the time gap between each
position of each flow [Andrei] the related
possibly the really related question
do you have enough data points to get the
estimate of a paleosecular variation?
[Boris] So, I can show you here..
[Andrei] but those are the poles or directions?
[Boris] for B1..so all these data are site mean directions
and so for this one [Andrei] that could be worked
with, I think, B1 i think could be
could be used for something right [Boris] yeah which we
I remember we estimated the s parameter
and it was quite high uh for these two
components I think way more than uh something like
between 25 and 30 something like this
[Andrei] It's not that high if [Boris] I have to check
that again but this is in the paper yeah
[Andrei] if you if you can get to the high latitude
then it's not that high particularly okay thank
you very much great talk here congratulations
[Dan] Thank you, Andrei.
do we have any more questions
yes, Simon go ahead
[Simon] all right, that was a great talk,
thanks. I was just wondering about
you know this equatorial
dipole, is it possible that
there's another explanatio, where it's just like
the more a multi-polar field and it's a bit more
random than than an equatorial dipole, and how
does that equatorial dipole exist if it was that?
[Boris] yeah so for the multiple for
the multiple field I would say
of course I cannot really say
if which fraction it would be but,
something that I found interesting is
that this large PolarWander oscillations
we find a similar pattern
in blocks that are geographically
far away from each other, so to me that
seems to indicate that we need at least
a dominant contribution of a dipole, but
then that would need to be done in a
compare like.. make some modalization of what
we what kind of field we would.. could explain
the data but from this consistent argument I
would say that we need a contribution of a dipole
then for the existence of an equatorial dipole,
I know that this equatorial dipole is debated
and I know that geodynamo models are not
all happy with an equatorial dipole, because
because of the rotation of the Earth, we
would prefer to have an axial dipole field.
Interestingly then there might
be this effect of the Inner Core
crystallization, where the the flow in
the in the core could be very different.
So um i'm not sure we have the we don't really
know yet, but uh could it be that by combining
Earth planet without an Inner Core and a strong
heat flux heterogeneities, we could
get to this kind of solution yeah
[Simon] thank you
[Dan] all right, thank you Boris. Do
we have one more question
if not then let's all thank Boris again
with another virtual round of applause,
[Boris] thank you very much. [Dan] Let me
share my screen one more time
just before we head out of here reminded that
there are a couple of MagNetZ seminars coming up
pretty soon. The next one is already next week and
we will stay in the Eastern hemisphere time slot
until the end of August when we move
back to the western hemisphere time slot
and as always we are of course looking for more
speakers preferably early career scientists.
And as all the previous talks this presentation
will be uploaded to our YouTube channel make sure
to check it out and if you're watching this on
youtube right now then make sure to smash those
like and subscribe button, so you don't miss out on
any of our future uploads! and that's gonna be it
for today! thank you all for watching and
I hope to see you all again next time!